Guide to the Harry L. Sanders Planning Documents
Stanford University. Libraries.
Department of Special Collections and University Archives
Harry L. Sanders planning documents
1940-1970
SC0674
Sanders, Harry L., collector.
1.5 Linear feet
This collection includes reports, proposals, agenda, minutes, transcripts of public hearings, and other documents pertaining to development in San Francisco, especially Diamond Heights and the Western Addition, 1948-54; and reports, booklets, and brochures pertaining to planning in general, 1940-70. Of note in the latter group is the book MEMOS FROM RUSSIA 1969; A STUDY--INDUSTRIALIZATION OF THE BUILDING PROCESS IN RUSSIA AND ENGLAND, written and illustrated by Bill Caudill and privately printed in 1970 by the architectural firm Caudill Rowlett Scott.
Department of Special Collections and University Archives Green Library 557 Escondido Mall Stanford, CA 94305-6064 Email: specialcollections@stanford.edu Phone: (650) 725-1022 URL: http://library.stanford.edu/spc
Administrative Information
Provenance
Gift of Harry L. Sanders, 1995.
Information about Access
This collection is open for research.
Biographical/Historical Sketch
Harry L. Sanders came to Stanford in 1956 as associate director of planning. In 1960 he became director of planning, the University's first full-time director; he retired in 1976. In addition to managing the complex development of the campus, Sanders was a cofounder of the Society of College and University Planning, member of the design team for California State Highway 280, and planning consultant to Menlo College and Tulane University.
Description of the Collection
This collection includes reports, proposals, agenda, minutes, transcripts of public hearings, and other documents pertaining to development in San Francisco, especially Diamond Heights and the Western Addition, 1948-54; and reports, booklets, and brochures pertaining to planning in general, 1940-70. Of note in the latter group is the book MEMOS FROM RUSSIA 1969; A STUDY--INDUSTRIALIZATION OF THE BUILDING PROCESS IN RUSSIA AND ENGLAND, written and illustrated by Bill Caudill and privately printed in 1970 by the architectural firm Caudill Rowlett Scott.
Access Terms
Caudill, William Wayne.; Sanders, Harry L., collector.; Building --Russia.; Building --Soviet Union.; Cities and towns --Growth.; City planning --California --San Francisco.; Community development, Urban.; Construction industry --Russia.; Construction industry --Soviet Union.; Urban renewal --California --San Francisco.
Collection Contents
- Papers
  - San Francisco Planning Documents
    - City Planning, Dept. of, miscellaneous printed maps and drawings, 1948-49 (Box 1, Folder 1)
    - Diamond Heights: Land Acquisition Plan, n.d., and Redevelopment in Diamond Heights, 1950 (Box 1, Folder 2)
    - Diamond Heights: "San Francisco Moves Ahead on Diamond Height Redevelopment" (The American City Nov. 1951); transcript of public hearing on redevelopment of the Diamond Heights, Jan. 15, 1952; Report on Improved Properties..., Sept. 10, 1953; Documentation in Support of the Redevelopment Plan for the Diamond Heights Approved Redevelopment Project Area B-1, Nov. 18, 1953 (Box 1, Folder 3)
    - Health and Safety Code Community Redevelopment Law 1951 (CA Senate Bill No. 1031) (Box 1, Folder 4)
    - Housing Conservation Round Table, from house + home, Oct. 1953 (Box 1, Folder 5)
    - Redevelopment Agency, Public Hearing October 14, 1952 (transcript) (Box 1, Folder 6)
    - Redevelopment Agency, agenda and documents for meeting of Jan. 13, 1953 (Box 1, Folder 7)
    - Redevelopment Agency, agenda and documents for special meeting of June 4, 1953 (Box 1, Folder 8)
    - Redevelopment Agency, minutes, Sept. 15 and 29, 1953 (Box 1, Folder 9)
    - Redevelopment Agency, assorted documents, 1952-53 (Box 1, Folder 10)
    - Redevelopment Agency, court case documents, 1954 (Box 1, Folder 11)
    - South of Market Area: The Feasibility of Redevelopment in the South of Market Area, July 16, 1952; Recommendation for Designation of a South of Market Redevelopment Area, Feb. 17, 1953; The Selection of a Project Area in the South of Market Redevelopment Area, Nov. 27, 1953 (Box 1, Folder 12)
    - Western Addition: transcript of public hearing on redevelopment, June 3, 1948; map of suggested site development, n.d. (Box 1, Folder 13)
    - Western Addition: plans and reports, 1952-54 (Box 2, Folder 1)
    - Housing Authority, 8th annual report 1947 ("Down Through the Years; the Story of a People's Love for Their City" ) (Box 2, Folder 2)
    - Master Plan of San Francisco 1946: Studies for the Location of a Central Airline Bus Terminal; and Summary (Box 2, Folder 3)
    - Redevelopment in the John McLaren Park Area, July 1951 (Box 2, Folder 4)
  - General Planning Documents
    - Adams, Frederick J., Urban Planning Education in the United States, 1954 (Box 2, Folder 5)
    - American Institute of Planners 1965 National Convention: The Sierra Club Presents the Crucial Resource (Box 2, Folder 6)
    - Baltimore: Waverly, a Study in Neighborhood Conservation, 1940 (Box 2, Folder 7)
    - Blueprint for Neighborhood Conservation, a working manual by the Build American Better Council, 1953 (Box 2, Folder 8)
    - California cities: The Phantom Cities of California (California Tomorrow, 1963) and program from 55th annual conference of the League of California Cities, October 1953 (Box 2, Folder 9)
    - Chicago: Redevelopment Project No. 4 [residential area in near southwest side], 1949 (Box 2, Folder 10)
    - Federal Housing Administration, "How to Test Financial Soundness of Rental Housing Properties," 1951 (Box 2, Folder 11)
    - Holmes, Jeffrey, 20/20 Planning; a short history of the first twenty years of the Society for College and University Planning. 1985 (Box 2, Folder 12)
    - Memos from Russia – 1969; a study—industrialization of the building process in Russia and England. CRS [Caudill Rowlett Scott] Investigation 19. [Written by Bill Caudill] (Box 2, Folder 13)
    - Menlo Park (CA), master plan, 1952 (Box 3, Folder 1)
    - Palo Alto (CA), Parks and Recreation Policy Study, Sept. 1969 (Box 3, Folder 2)
    - Rehabilitation:
      - A Primer on Rehabilitation under Local Law Enforcement (National Association of Real Estate Boards, 1952) (Box 3, Folder 3)
      - Rehabilitation as a Business (National Association of Real Estate Boards, 1954) (Box 3, Folder 3)
    - Roads:
      - Roadside Protection in California; a Handbook for Local Action (California Roadside Council 1952) (Box 3, Folder 4)
      - Roadside Protection (American Automobile Association, 1951) (Box 3, Folder 4)
      - The Modern Freeway – and Billboards (brochure by the California Roadside Council 1952) (Box 3, Folder 4)